Finding aid to the Margaret Storrs Grierson papers CA.MS.00028
Smith College Archives
Margaret Storrs Grierson papers
1800-1999
1918-1997
Smith College Archives
Grierson, Margaret Storrs.
CA.MS.00028
5.75 linear feet (6 containers)
Margaret Storrs Grierson was an alumna of Smith College, Instructor of English and Philosophy, archivist, one of the founders and first director of the Sophia Smith Collection. The collection contains biographical material, correspondence (especially with Nina E. Browne, Marine Leland, and with family members), diaries, financial records, passports, manuscripts, publications and includes historic writings, documents, and photographs on the Storrs, Cooper, Rankin, and Barnes families.
Biographical / Historical
Margaret Storrs was born June 29, 1900 to Lucius S. Storrs and Mary Cooper Storrs in Denver, Colorado. Her mother was the daughter of Job Adams Cooper, governor of Colorado (1889-1891) and had grown up in the whirl of social, business and political life in Denver and Colorado. Mr. Storrs was a business administrator who spent most of his life with rail transportation companies in the United States. The Storrs family was originally from Connecticut.
From the time of her birth until 1907 her family's life centered on Denver, Colorado and Bozeman, Montana. However Mr. Storrs advancement in the rail industry took the family to Boston, Massachusetts in February 1907 with the family eventually living in Brookline by July 1907. They then moved to Springfield, Massachusetts in October 1908, where her brother Lucius S., Jr. was born on December 10, 1910. Another job advancement found the family moving to New Haven, Connecticut in 1911 where her parents remained until after Ms. Storrs had graduated from Smith College. The family traveled frequently to visit the extended family by automobile and railroad, especially visits to Denver, Colorado.
Ms. Storrs entered Smith College in 1918 and graduated A.B. in 1922. She did graduate work at Bryn Mawr College and she studied at University College of the University of London from 1924-1925. From 1925-1930 she taught philosophy at Bryn Mawr while completing her dissertation and graduated with the Ph.D. in 1930.
In 1930 Ms. Storrs returned to Northampton, Massachusetts and by the mid-1930s purchased a home at 66 Massasoit Street that she shared with Marine Leland, who was a member of the Smith College French Department. They shared this house together until Prof. Leland's death in 1983. On December 7, 1938 Ms. Storrs married Sir Herbert Grierson in Edinburgh, Scotland. They returned to Northampton but after February 1939 until Sir Herbert's death in February 1960 they lived apart, however she continued to use the name Mrs. Margaret Storrs Grierson for the remainder of her life.
Upon her return to Smith College in 1930 until 1936 she taught philosophy. In 1940 she was appointed the college archivist and in 1942 she was given the additional duties of executive secretary of the Friends of the Smith College Library. It was as a special project of the Friends that the Sophia Smith Collection came into being. Mrs. Grierson was its first director and held all three of these positions until her retirement in 1965. In her position as head of the Sophia Smith Collection Mrs. Grierson traveled throughout the United States and the world to assemble the manuscript materials that are so important in documenting the history of women.
After her retirement in 1965 Mrs. Grierson turned her attention to an accumulation of papers inherited from her parents related to the history of her family. From the late 1960s through the 1980s Mrs. Grierson sought information on the family and wrote (unpublished) an extensive history of the Storrs family and its ancestors including the Cooper, Rankin and Barnes families. Mrs. Grierson said she was not interested in genealogy but in the documented historical facts of these families, their movements and lives in the United States.
Repeated health problems forced Mrs. Grierson to sell her 66 Massasoit Street home in the early 1990s and she took an apartment on Crescent Street in Northampton where she lived until advanced problems found her in nursing homes. She died on December 12, 1997 at the Linda Manor Extended Care Facility in Leeds, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
The Margaret Storrs Grierson papers contain materials related to Mrs. Grierson's career at Smith College as student, professor, college archivist and one of the founders and first director of the Sophia Smith Collection. In addition, there are her historic writings on the Storrs, Cooper, Rankin, Barnes and other related families and documents related to this work. There are biographical items, correspondence (especially with Nina E. Browne and with family members), diaries, financial records, passports, manuscripts and publications. Also included are photographs of the families as well as correspondence in relationship to Grierson's companion, Marine Leland.
The family papers are a mixture of documents (usually arranged under an individual or family name) and may contain a mixture of materials: historic documents and letters, photographs, printed materials and correspondence that spans from ca. 1800 to 1997. The files are essentially as Mrs. Grierson arranged them; in addition, the files contain correspondence by Mrs. Grierson and to her in her pursuit of documentation on particular family members. Also in the files are notations by Mrs. Grierson on the disposition of some historic documents that were once part of files but were placed in historic archives she deemed a more appropriate location for them to reside.
Related Material
Hague, Amy E., "'Never Another Season of Silence': Laying the Foundation of the Sophia Smith Collection, 1942-1965," Revealing Women's Life Stories: Papers from the 50th Anniversary Celebration of the Sophia Smith College, Smith College, Northampton, Massachusetts, September 1982. [Northampton, Massachusetts]: Smith College, 1995, p. 9-27.
Lyman, Susan E., "Margaret Storrs Grierson," Smith Alumnae Quarterly 56 (Summer 1965): 212.
Hague, Amy, "Margaret Storrs Grierson, June 29, 1900-December 12, 1997," Imposing Evidence: Newsletter of the Sophia Smith Collection 1 (Feb. 1998): 1.
10.9 Administrative files, Smith College Archives and Sophia Smith Collection [Portions of these files may be restricted.]
52. Marine Leland Papers, Smith College Archives
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Margaret Storrs Grierson Papers were created and assembled by Mrs. Grierson during her lifetime and donated to the Smith College Archives.
- Series 1 - General
  - Biographical materials, 1960s-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - MSG and the Sophia Smith Collection [1] "Revealing Women's Life Stories", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - MSG and the Sophia Smith Collection [2] "No Documents-No History" paper by Anke Voss-Hubbard, 199- (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - MSG and the Sophia Smith Collection [3]"Agents of Social Change: Providing Access to Key Twentieth Century Women's Manuscript Collections", July 1, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Birth and death certificates, 1900; 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Will and probate materials, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Passports and international travel documents, 1932-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - MSG's interview with Ruth Solie on Sophie Drinker, 27 Sept 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Botany lecture notes, Prof. William Francis Ganong, Smith College, Botany 11, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bryn Mawr College commencement program, 5 June 1929 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - MSG Endowment Fund-Contributors list, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - MSG Endowment Fund-Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - MSG Endowment Fund-Accounting papers, 1985-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Retirement party, 23 April 1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Real estate (Denham Building, Denver and other property), 1939-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Herbert Grierson documents, 1938-1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mayflower Descendants documents, etc., 1952-1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memorial service, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letter opener (carved tortoise shell) and large decorative clip (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Analysis of MSG's handwriting, 1922? (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Series II - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Formal portraits of MSG (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs in Smith College settings, 1930s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of MSG, her family and friends, 1900s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs related to Lucius Storrs, Jr. (Luke) and Ruth Storrs and family, 1930s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Caryl Storrs Castellion and family, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Margaret Storrs Eaton (Peggy) and family, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Eastons and Riordans, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of painting of Mather & Susan Cleveland family, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Eatons, Riordans and some with Rylands and Champie-Flood-Tewksby, 1960s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Great, greats, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of friends, 1910s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series III - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, general, 1922-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, general, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, general, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, general, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, general, 1986-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, general, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, general, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, general - Christmas, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with Lucius S. Storrs, Jr. (Luke), 1970-1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with Caryl Storrs Castellion, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence received upon MSG's death, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence received upon retirement, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence upon receiving the Smith College Medal, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence on the 40th anniversary of the Sophia Smith Collection, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Marine Leland memorial service bulletin, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence received upon the death of Marine Leland, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence received upon the death of Marine Leland, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence received upon MSG's 95th birthday, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Postcard received - "Pick the Pickaninnies puzzle", 1908 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence from Charles Frederick Harrold, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence to Nina Browne, 1942-1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence from Nina Browne, 1943-1951 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence from David Staines on article on "The Study of Canada at Smith," includes a draft by MSG on Canadian studies at Smith, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence to Robert Loeffler, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence from Josephine Ott, 1983-1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence to Mary Shaw Newman (Mrs. Robert B. Newman), 1992-1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence from Linda Peavy and Ursula Smith, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence notebook, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Series IV - Writings (Box 2)
  - Ph.D. dissertation, Bryn Mawr College - The Relation of Carlyle to Kant and Fichte, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Daily notes (photocopy), 1918-1922 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Quarterly pieces (drafts), 1940-1974; undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous pieces (drafts), 1919-1982; undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - On Nina Eliza Browne (draft), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - On Romanticism (draft), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sketches of persons in Smith College history known by MSG (drafts), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - MSG's "One basket (all eggs) - v. 1: Household accounts and other activities (notebook), 1935-1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - MSG's "One basket (all eggs) - v. 2: Household accounts and other activities (notebook), 1977-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Canadian year - v. 1 (diary), 28 Sept.-30 Nov. 1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Canadian year - v. 2 (diary), 1 Dec. 1967-31 Jan. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Canadian year - v. 3 (diary), 1 Feb.-23 April 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Canadian year - v. 4 (diary), 24 April-1 June 1958 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series V - Family history files
  - Confessions of an Archival Aunt: or, An Explanation of the Handling of Family Papers, 199? (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Family history correspondence, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 1a)
  - Correspondence on disposition, 1980s- (Box 2, Folder 1b)
  - Family history, by MSG, 1980s (Box 2)
    - Family Forebears, v.1: Immigration to America, 1620-1640 (draft) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Family Forebears, v.2: New England Colonies, 1640-about 1690 (draft) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Family Forebears, v.3: Through Colonial Days, circa 1690-1776 (draft) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Family Forebears, v.4: Between Two Wars, 1776-1862 (draft) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Family Forebears, v.5: Mary Louise Cooper and Lucius Seymour Storrs (draft) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Family Forebears - Appendix I and II to v.5: Biographical sketches of relatives. I: descendants from Romulus and Olivia Barnes and from Charles and Maria Cooper - II: descendants from Lucius and Suzanne Storrs and from Joseph and Janet Rankin (draft) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Storrs genealogy (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Oddments related to the Storrs family (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mary Cooper Storrs & Lucius S. Storrs marriage, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Mary Cooper Storrs, 1890s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mary Cooper Storrs - Miscellaneous items, 1890-1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Margaret Storrs Journal kept by her Mother" (Mary Cooper Storrs), 1900-1915 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Mary Cooper Storrs 5-year line-a-day diary, 1939-1943 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - MSG extracts from the 5-year diary (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Medal of Mary Cooper Storrs - National Society of the Colonial Dames of America-Connecticut (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lucius S. Storrs-Photographs and certificates, 1920s-19-- (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Medals and badges of Lucius S. Storrs (a) Medal of the Sons of the American Revolution; (b) Badge of the American Railway Association, Lucius S. Storrs, President, 1917; (c) Delegate Badge & Ribbon-Connecticut Delegation to the Republican Convention, Cleveland, 1924; (d) Badge & Ribbon, Union Station Celebration, Mary 3-5, 1939, Lucius S. Storrs, Executive Committee; (e) Memorial coins: 1919 World Fair - Los Angeles, Calif., Transportation Week, March 22-28, 1937; (f) Lapel pins - Ribbon (?) - American flag, 1910s-1930s (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Millicent Ward Whitt correspondence to MSG, 1950s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of pastel portraits of Lucius S. Storrs, Lucius S. Storrs, Jr. and Ruth Storrs - two portraits of Native Americans (Box 3, Folder 18a)
  - Annie Cleary (maid in the home of Lucius Storrs and Mary Cooper Storrs), by MSG (Box 3, Folder 18b)
  - Correspondence from Sydney Whitt, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Millicent Ward Whitt - Poetry, 1940s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Millicent Ward Whitt - Bozeman, Montana items, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - John C. Rankin correspondence to MSG, 1980s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Wesley Rankin correspondence to MSG, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Elsie Ward Travis (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - M. Travis Lane, 1960-1990 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Hannah Lane, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Olivia Denham Cooper (Mrs. Edwin Kassler) - Ruth Kassler Alexander - Edwin S. Kassler, Jr. - Genevieve Kassler Brock, 1940s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Charles Job Cooper - Lillian Winter - John Adams - Alan Bradford - Jerome Rich, 1890-1990s (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Genevieve Pearl Cooper (Mrs. Dwight E. Ryland) - Jane Dodd - John Findley Ryland, 1950s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Olivia Denham Barnes, 1878-1970s (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Denham - Samuel; Mathilda Goodale; Louisa Farnham; Butler, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Romulus Edwin Barnes, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Dan Storrs and family - Origen, Selima Seymour; Juba; Maria Hutchins; Delia Waterman, 1894-1977 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Gen. Lucius Storrs and Susan Young Caryl Storrs, 1800s-1930s (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Bigelow (Maria Storrs) - Albert; Allen Gilman; Walter Storrs; Lucius Seymour, 1890s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Rosenbury (Charlotte Storrs) -Charles D.; Charles Ward; Susan Greene, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Introducing Caryl B. Storrs (draft by MSG), 1970s (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Caryl Buell Storrs - documents, photographs, etc., 1910s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Origen Seymour Storrs and Janet Rankin Storrs, 1860s-1910s (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Janet Rankin portraits (1) - at Ingham University, 1850s (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Janet Rankin portrait (2) (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Janet Rankin - pins and locket (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Janet Rankin papers, 1850s (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Janet Rankin notebook - at Ingham University, 1850s (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - John D. Rankin, 1880s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Joseph Rankin and Janet Allen, 1840s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Daguerreotype of John and Amelia Rankin (?), 18uu (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Joseph Rankin (1833-1886), 1880s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Benjamin Clark Caryl family - Benjamin, Jr.; Alexander Hamilton; Elizabeth Haskins; Catherine; Cotton Warner; Charlotte Coleman; Charles Caryl Coleman - includes MSG's drafts (a) The Caryl Family - (b) The Caryl Family and Charles Caryl Coleman, 19 -1970s (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Job Adams Cooper, 1890s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Charles Isaac Colwell & Mary Greenough Barnes (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Pursuit of Barnes - largely correspondence by MSG and responses, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Pursuit of Caryl, Cooper, Storrs - largely correspondence by MSG and responses, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Lucius Caryl Storrs and Charlotte Case, 1908-1970s (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Origen Seymour Storrs (1840-1867), 1860s-1915 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Rev. Romulus Barnes, 1830s-19uu (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Charles Montgomery Barnes and Ellen Moore, 1880s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Samuel Denham Barnes and Georgiana Parker, 1880s-1900s (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Francis Carey and Mary Louisa Barnes, 1900s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Joseph Avery Barnes and Olive Davidson (or Davison) - Frederick Andrew Knox, 1870s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Olivia Lee (Lillie) Barnes and William E. Dodds, 1900s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Jane Olivia Barnes Cooper (1), 1900s-1967 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Jane Olivia Barnes Cooper (1) - letters, 1863-1900s (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Frederick Andrew Colwell correspondence with MSG, 1970s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Selima Storrs McHarg - Rev. William Neil; Williams Storrs; Charles King, 1860s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 66)
- Series VI - Oversized
  - Card file - "Inactive Address Files" (Box 4)
  - Card file - Books read - "Some books to read" - "Family forebears files" - MSG secretaries & assistants, cleaning women, seamstress, physicians and other lists - Address file "Current Active Files" (Box 4)
  - Romulus Barnes as a young man - Pastel portrait (Box 4)
  - Presentation item to Lucius Seymour Storrs from The Connecticut Company (Box 4)
  - Book - Job Adams Cooper, Sixth Governor of the State of Colorado and his Wife, Jane Olivia Barnes Cooper, by Philip K. Alexander, Jr. (typescript), 1978 (Box 4)
  - Book - The Storrs Family: Genealogical and Other Memoranda, collected and complied by Charles Storrs. New York: Privately Printed, 1886. (Box 4)
  - Parchment - "To Our Retiring President, Lucius S. Storrs" from the Los Angeles Railway Corp., April 19, 1939 and other documents on the occasion (Box 5)
  - Presentation book to Lucius S. Storrs from the American Electric Railway Association, May 2, 1929 (Box 5)
  - Portrait of Herbert Hoover, autographed to Lucius S. Storrs, 1920s or 1930s (Box 5)
  - Photograph - Broad Street (New York City), Victory Day, Nov. 1918 (Box 5)
  - Photographs of business associates of Lucius S. Storrs, 1920s-1930s (?) (Box 5)
  - Portrait of Lucius S. Storrs, Jr. (by Fabian Bachrach), 1950s (?) (Box 5)
  - Certificate to Lucius S. Storrs from the United States Council of National Defense, 1919 (Box 5)
  - Certificate to Lucius S. Storrs from the Society of Colonial Wars in the State of Connecticut, 1922 (Box 5)
  - "Genealogical Record of the Storrs Family in the United States," compiled and arranged by Charles Storrs. Brooklyn, N.Y., 1881 (Box 5)
    General
    Scroll - photocopy of this scroll is in the MSG papers, Series V, folder 8
  - Sixteen books - presentation copies to MSG (Box 6)